Alexandria Fire Department Records, 1794-1893
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Fire Department Records, 1794-1893
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
267
2 boxes (0.35 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Milton Penn, August 1991.
Accruals
Additional materials donated in 1995.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Alexandria Fire Department included five different volunteer fire companies during the period covered in these records. The first was the Friendship Fire Company, founded in 1774 and located on 107 South Alfred Street. Next was the Sun Fire Company in 1775. The Relief Fire Company was begun in 1788 and was located at 315 Prince Street. The Star Fire Company was started in 1799 and combined with the Friendship in 1852. Its new name was the Columbia Engine Company #4, when it was equipped with a new steam-powered fire engine in 1883. It was located at 109 South St. Asaph Street. In 1827, the Hydraulion Fire Company was founded. It was located at 1210 Cameron Street.
Each household in Alexandria purchased fire insurance and was assigned a specific fire company in case of disaster. The volunteer fire companies would not assist anyone without a plaque on their domicile or business, proving they were legitimately covered with insurance from the Fire Insurance Company of Alexandria.
Scope and Content
The papers in this collection cover all of the fire companies' business and legal transactions over a span of one hundred years. The canceled checks show the many expenditures necessary to outfit, maintain, and operate the volunteer fire companies. There are also many receipts from commercial firms who provisioned, repaired, serviced and supplied the volunteer fire companies. The Alexandria Common Council appropriated money each year to cover the entire Fire Department.
Many reports to the Common Council are included. These contain appropriations for the fire companies, fire warden appointees and resignations, construction and repair of fire houses, minutes of Fire Department meetings, the establishment of a Fire Department Board of Directors and the enactment of laws covering fire house bells and assembly at fire houses.
One report from the Fire Department, dated May 8, 1860, describes how much usable hose each fire company has on-hand and requests purchase of more hose, in linear feet. A quarterly report dated August 15, 1851 lists the number of members in each fire company: The Sun had 111; the Relief, 63; the Friendship, 76; the Star, 47; and the Hydraulion, 52.
Arrangement
The material is arranged chronologically by type of correspondence or business-related transaction. Arrangement repeated for Box 267B added in 1995.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Alexandria vertical file: Fire Department, Old
Charles Sampson collections, Box 53 and Box 126-128.
Index Terms
Fire departments--Virginia--Alexandria
Contents List
- Canceled checks to various businesses for fire department services, September 3, 1844 - December 5, 1859 (Box-folder 267A:1)
- Canceled checks to various businesses for fire department services, January 6, 1860 - December 2, 1865 (Box-folder 267A:2)
- Canceled checks to various businesses for fire department services, April 30, 1866 - October 20, 1875 (Box-folder 267A:3)
- Receipts for services and goods rendered to fire department from commercial firms, April 10, 1837 - November 27, 1851 (Box-folder 267A:4)
- Receipts for services and goods rendered to fire department from commercial firms, January 1, 1854 - November 27, 1868 (Box-folder 267A:5)
- Receipts for services and goods rendered to fire department from commercial firms, February 13, 1869 - December 31, 1872 (Box-folder 267A:6)
- Receipts for services and goods rendered to fire department from commercial firms, January 1, 1873 - March 23, 1876 (Box-folder 267A:7)
- Alexandria Common City Council documents concerning the Fire Department, January 17, 1794 - December 29, 1851 (Box-folder 267A:8)
- Alexandria Common City Council documents concerning the Fire Department, January 7, 1852 - October 3, 1893 (Box-folder 267A:9)
- 2nd Ward 1858 Engine and Fire Dept. Gauges and Measures of Wood and Lumber - Election book(?) (Box-folder 267B:1)
- Deed and receipt to the Mayor of Alexandria from the Court of the County of Fairfax, 1794-1796 (Box-folder 267B:2)
- Expenditures, 1847-1852 (Box-folder 267B:3)
- Reports - Quarterly Night Watch (September and December 1851); Station House (January 16, 1870 and February 27, 1871) (Box-folder 267B:4)
- Acts Appropriating Salaries, 1859-1865 (Box-folder 267B:5)
- Petition of Guy Atkinson and W. Yeaton to city council and letter to proprietor of theater regarding needed repairs, n.d. (Box-folder 267B:6)
- Petitions - Thomas Taylor for Clerk (1845); to celebrate Thanksgiving (n.d.) (Box-folder 267B:7)
- Miscellaneous - non Fire Department receipts and documents; guard and picket passes, 1864 (Box-folder 267B:8)
- Mayor's office/City Council correspondence, 1820-1849 (Box-folder 267B:9)
- Mayor's office/City Council correspondence, 1851-1859 (Box-folder 267B:10)
- Mayor's office/City Council correspondence, 1862-1870 (Box-folder 267B:11)
- Checks, 1844-1883 (Box-folder 267B:12)
- Miscellaneous bills and receipts, 1794; 1835; 1840s (Box-folder 267B:13)
- Miscellaneous bills and receipts, 1850s (Box-folder 267B:14)
- Miscellaneous bills and receipts, 1860s (Box-folder 267B:15)
- Miscellaneous bills and receipts, 1870s (Box-folder 267B:16)